
<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-cherry-blossom-trees/selected-articles</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85042462/1909-10-19/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=Mikado+Cherry+Trees</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>MANY CHERRY TREES
SHIPPED BY MIKADO
JAPAN SENDS U. S. OVER 2000
FINE SPECIMENS
Many Saplings from Orient Will B«
Planted Along Potomac and Riv
erside Driveways Mrs.
Taft Recipient
WASHINGTON, Oct. 18.—When tha
honorary commercial commissioners of
Japan arrives in Washington, Novem
ber 1, they will be taken on an auto
mobile ride which will include Poto
mac drive, along which 2000 cherry
trees to be presented to this country
by the emperor of Japan are to be
planted.
The shipment of the trees and the
planting thereof have been entrusted
to Toraklro Watase, proprietor of a
Tokio plant and seed company, who
is one of the commissioners.
Speaking of the gift of the emperor
to the city of Washington, Mr. Watase
said the trees would be sent to Mrs.
Taft, wife of the president, and by
her presented to the government for
transplanting- along- Potomac drive.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85042462/1909-10-19/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=Mikado+Cherry+Trees</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The emperor of Japan Is sending to
New York also a large number of
cherry trees to be planted along River
side drive and Grant's tomb.
In Japan, the land of the cherry
blossom, there are many beautiful
legends about the trees and flower of
the cherry.
The blossom of the Japanese cherry
is of a peculiarly delicate beauty, and
there is a tradition in Japan that if
that same tone appears in the blos
soms of the Japanese cherry planted
in another country, that country can
he taken and subjugated by Japan.
Mr. Watase is authority for the
statement that while many Japanese
cherry trees have been brought to the
United States, the color of the bloa
eoms, although just as beautiful, is
unlike the blossom which appears in
Japan.</text>
      </result>
            <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82016187/1909-12-23/ed-1/?sp=5&amp;q=Cherry+Trees+Mikado</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Our new Potomac Park down beyond
the monument is to be beautified by
Japanese cherry trees Col Cosby Su
perintendent of Public Buildings and
Grounds has been informed by Jukio
OzakI the Mayor of Tokyo Japan that
the 2000 cherry trees which were pre
sented to the city of Washington have
arrived at Seattle and will be shipped
at once to this city Tho Mayor of
Tokyo said in his letter It gives me
great pleasure to inform you that the
corporation of Tokyo at a recent meet
ing of its Councils resolved to present
2000 Japanese cherry trees to the Gov
ernment of the United States for tho
use of the city of Washington And
the Mayor goes on to say The cherry
trees are extensively cultivated in this
country and are the most admired of
the flowering trees Ten of the most
representative kinds have been selected
and I beg to assure you that it will re
main to the citizens of Tokyo a pleas
ing memory as well as a matter of civic
pride to know that their small offering
will be permitted to contribute to the
advancement of the beautiful Capital
of the great Republic which they all
admire</text>
      </result>
            <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86069675/1910-01-19/ed-1/?sp=5&amp;q=Cherry+Trees</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Japanese Cherry Trees Presented to Mrs. Taft
The Emperor of Japan's re-
membrance of President Taft's
great enjoyment of the cherry
blossom festival season when in
Japan has taken the graceful form
of the presentation to Mrs. Taft
of three carloads of young cherry
trees, and they are now in Wash-
ington.
The greatest care has been taken
all the way from the land of the
Mikado to keep the temperature
at an even stage so that the trees
arrive in perfect condition.
In appreciation, the opportunity
for a cherry blossom season at the
National Capital has included the
delivery of the trees to the District
Commissioners, and rows of
them lining the Potomac Boule-
vard will be a beautiful feature of
that imposing thoroughfare.</text>
      </result>
            <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1910-01-29/ed-1/?sp=6&amp;q=Mikado+Cherry+Trees</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>TO DESTROY JAPANESE TREES.
Gifts from Tokio to Wasnington Found
To Be Badly Diseased.
Washington, Jan. 2S.— Regret has been
expressed by the President and by Mrs.
Taft because two thousand Japanese
cherry trees presented by the municipality
of Toklo to this government for use In the
national capita' have been found to be
Ir.fected with root gall worms, certain dis
eases and Insect pests, some of the latter
hitherto unknown in this country. The
trees were to have been planted in Poto
m;\c Park, wl^.ich Mrs. Taft did much last
year to have made the outdoor boulevard
and meeting place of social ashington.
The Secretar of Agriculture s.,- .m
It necessary to recommend the destruc
tion of the trees. Secretary Knox lias ex
ptm i to the Japanese Ambassador the
regret of the government authorities that
the gift cannot be used, and Colonel Cosby,
in charge of Public Building" and Grounds,
has conveyed reyrets to the Mayor of
Toklo.</text>
      </result>
            <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045433/1910-10-16/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Cherry+Trees</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>As a mark of heartfelt friendship, the Emperor of Japan sent 1,008 cherry trees to Mrs. Taft recently. 
  However, they became infected and did not survive.</text>
      </result>
            <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82016187/1910-12-22/ed-1/?sp=5&amp;q=Cherry+Trees</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>It will be remembered that tho Em
peror of Japan last Spring sent several
thousand Japanese cherry trees to Mrs
Taft to be placed along the Iotomac
Drive which she originated These
cherry trees were found to be infected
witha peculiar injurious Japanese in
sect and for fear they would contami
nate the cherry trees In this country
the whole lot was burned It is now
announced that the Japanese authori
ties are sending another consignment
of cherrj trees that have been exam
ined and shown to be clear of all dis
ease</text>
      </result>
            <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1912-03-06/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=Cherry+Trees</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>CHERRY TREES ON THE WAY
Long Delayed ?Tapanese Gift to
City Soon to Arrive.
Th? long looked for chfrry trees which
the Japanese government offered to ?ara?
sent to this city a! th. tin-.c of the b?ud?
Pulton celebration will be here in a
few days Tho consignment, which In?
trudes 2,100 y??ung cherrv tr?es, ar?
rived last week in Seattle, and is now be?
ing shipped to this city oveT th? Great
Northern Railroad.
Park Gawmlaslom saM yes?
terday that he. had written to the De?
partment ?-.f Agriculture In Washington
to send man here to examine the
trees to make sure that no ruinous tree
is being import?-?-! at the same
time. In "\plainlng tl?- delay of the
trees th< Park Commissioner paid the
first ti i b prepared for shipment w re
found to have blight.
"Th?n th* Japanese authorities prom
iyo,^ to have these trees reach here fust
about this time," slid the Commission?
er. >hlch shows the calculating DOW?
era of the Japan
The problem of wher" to plant su b
a number of trees is bothering the Com?
missioner Charles D. Lay. the land?
scape, architect, hus r*en nsked to pre?
pare plans at once, because it will be
net?essarv to plant the trees as soon ^s
the weather is favorable.
The Japanese interested in the platine
of the tre*s want manv of them planted
around Grant's tomb Last winter n
bronze tablet, on which was engraved a
scene of Grant's tomb surrounded wj?h
the cherry trees, nraa presented bv Jap?
anese -it:zeris. ?nd is taken as indicat?
ing where at l^ist some of them mvist
go to m??et th" expectations of the
donor;</text>
      </result>
            <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045433/1912-03-28/ed-1/?sp=12&amp;q=Cherry+Trees</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>
            <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1919-04-07/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=Cherry+Trees</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>GLIMPSE QF NIPPON
NEAR TIDAL BASIN
Japan has come to the United
States Just a little bit of the Flowery
Kingdom, to be sure tmt enough to
make even the most unimaginative
person long to see "cherry felosjoa
time In Nippon.
Down at the Tidal Basin, the other
side of the Monument, a galaxy of
Japanese cherry trees are Is full and
fragrant bloom blooms that are try
Ing to say with U. their delicate
pinkness and sweetness that -spring
Is here, that they live "but to weave
garlands for her costumes and
wreath lor her hair.
Yesterday every member of the
Japanese embassy made a pilgrimage
to the- cherry trees from their own
far-away country stood In wonder
and delight at the sight of the flowers
they love so well. It was like being
transported "back to Japan for a few
happy moments, they said.
But it's only a sample of what
Japan really looks like, they declare,
for In their country the trees are tea
times as big as our trees, although
not a whit lovelier, for the climate
here Is ideal for the full flowering of
the- Japanese trees.
Th cherry trees' came tc as
straight from Japan several years
ago and begged a home in this jeeaa
try. </text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1913-04-06/ed-1/?sp=10&amp;q=Cherry+Trees</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>In all the riot of blossoms which hav
burseohevl forth In Potomac Park wttM
In the last week, to make that tract
the, most gorgeous anywhere la th
jietrict, therr ia none which show morn
delicate beauty than the Moons oa tM
Japenese cherry trees which were ate
rented to the U.iUed States by the gov
-.'rnment of Japan a year ago. TMat
fragrant, beautiful trees are blooratnjjf
Jers for the first time. The river Urle
Yom the Virginia bride up to Twealy
slxtr street la fragrant with them. anA."
thousands have stopped their carriages
to admire the delicacy and beauty Of
the blooms. j.
Unlike the-domestic cherry tha Ja
3rtrc variety Jeans more to bloom taA
It dos to fruit. The chief strength of
the trees seems-to be spent In pttittrii
foith tha. wonderful clusters of .blos
soms which cover the'llmbs. The tries
have been plinttd for just a little mora
Uvan a year and of course have hot
obtained any beauty in regard to c3
roimation. The pruning kalfe hast pkk
opportunity to work toward symetry
and the branches spread awkwariiy
aioe the main stem.
BtosMSAs Are BeaitifuL
The blossoms, however, are as bau
ilful now as they wll be in yeaji'ta
rome and make theobserver fcrget UW
shape of the tree. In appearance
0:00ms are a delicate pink shading
tTmost to white In some instaaeasV
.'avh cluster is made up of dozens of
ir dividual blossoms which are forsS-l
-omewhat like the wild rose.
A little over a year ago the Depart
ment of .Agriculture received a conslt
raent of several hundred cherry trsei
from Japan- One of the shipaseata
trees was found to be infected HS4
scale disease, and. far t ear U&amp;t sB8
new tree plague might spreadfrom th
District, the heada of the, deffrtssent
considered destroying the wholf lot Jf
several hundred trees. Ctete txiwto-
tlon disclosed that the. trees slTectad
were in the minority, and. tepwed;
lng out 'the affected ones, the remainder
were planted. A
The original Intention JP
the cherry .trees all over the District of
Columbia., but after the scale waa MM
covered the plan was changed and
trees planted along the river bank Id
Pdtomac Park. In this location
are practically segregated, and. if .th
scale develops further. It will be a cess
paratlvely simple matter to keep .th
disease in a restricted area until It Is
stamped out..
Park Gay With Blooali.
Although the Japanese cherry bl;
soms are the most delicately beautiful
in the park., thai tract is now filled witA
blossoms or every description. Troni
the ragged Scotch broom to the appli
trees almost evcrji color and shape tad
be seen. "The mild winter. combine
with almost ideal weather conditions fr
the development of blossoms' has madi
the; .blooms, more beautiful and larger,, t
than Tor severaf years.
Particularly beautiful are two grpups
ot apple trijes alonp the western edge
?f the basin. Each group is of three
rces, and every tree Is well nigh per?
feet. Th blooms cover every limb with
an almost solid mass of delicate white.
Other groups of plum and native cherry
trees follow" close upon tht apples la c
point of beautv. and the whole comblh
to make Po;omac Tark fragrantly beau
tlful and riotous witn spring.</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-assassination-franz-ferdinand</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1914-06-29/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Ferdinand</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Keep the lines and fix:
ARCHDUKE PARRIED
BOMB WITH ARM
Warded Off the Deadly
Missile from Himself
and Wife.
MET HIS END LATER
BY BULLET WOUND
Crowd in Both Cases Tried to
Make Assassins Pay Sum
inarily for Crime.
my Cable ?o Th? TrfbUM 1
Vienna. .Tune 28. The following de?
tails of the assassination of Archduke
Francis Ferdinand and his wife arc
now available. At 10 a. m. the arch?
duke, with the duchess, left the mili?
tary camp in an automobile for the
Town Hall. The car halted for some
minutes while a number of young
girls in festive attire greeted the heir
i.pparent and the duchess, who accept?
ed some flowers from them and spoke
a few kindly words.
The car moved on, but ?earctl'y had
it gone more than a few yards when a
man, who has since been identified as a
printer named Gabrlnovics, sprang out
from the crowd and hurled a bomb
full at the royal car. The archduke
himself warded it off w.th his arm
and it fell at the back of the car and.
rebounding on the roid, exploded.
The automobile had by this time
moved s?ve ?1 yari. and the full force
of the exp ision fell on the following
automobi.??, which contained four mem?
bers of the Archduke's suite. They
were Count Boos-Waldeck, Baron
Ilummerskireh, Countess von Lanjus,
lady in waiting, and Lieutenant Colo?
nel von Merizzi, aide-de-camp.
The last named received a splinter
in the neck and was badly hurt. The
royal chauffeur, at the direction of the
Archduke, immediately brought the
car to a standstill. In the mean time
the would-be assassin was seized by
the police, who 1k?1 the greatest diffi?
culty in saving him from the fury of
the crowd. The Archduke, after ascer?
taining the extent of the injuries to
his aide-de-camp and seeing that he
was being medically attended to, gave
the order to proceed, and the royal car
soon afterward arrived at the Town
Hall.
With his wife he spent half an hour
inspecting the Town Hall. The Arch?
duke then stated he was going to the
garrison hospital to see how Colonel
von Merizzi was progressing. Escorted
by the town councillors he descended
the step? leading to the entrance of
the buile g, re-entered the automo?
bile with his wife and drove off. The
car reached the corner of Franzjosef
and Rudolph sts. when two shots in
close succession rang out.
The first struck the Archduke in the
right cheek, inflicting a fhortal wound,!
while the second penetrated the body j
of the Duchess, severing a main artery.
She sank unconscious into the arms of
her husband, who a few seconds after?
ward also fainted. With all speed the
car was driven by the chauffeur to the
Town Hall, but almost before the doc?
tor could reach their side both had ex
pired.
The ar-sassin, who was a Servian stu*
dent named Gavro Prinzip, was seize?'!
and disarmed. The crowd made I
fierate attempt it? drug him from th?-!
protecting police, but the latter sue-,
ceeded in conveying him unharmed t*
the police station.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1914-06-29/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Ferdinand</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text></text>
      </result>
            <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045433/1914-06-29/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=archduke+Archduke+Bosnia+EMPEROR+Emperor+Ferdinand+Franz+Josef+Sarajevo</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>
AUSTRIAN HEIR AND HIS
WIFE SHOT TO DEATH
AETER ESCAPING BOMB
Archduke Franz Ferdinand and Morganatic Spouse Assas
sinated by Youth in Streets of Sarajevo After
Infernal Machine Hurled by Anarchistic
Compositor Fails to Explode
Until After They Pass.
COURTS OF EUROPE PLUNGED INTO MOURNING j
AGED EMPEROR MAY NOT SURVIVE THE SHOCK
Ej-t Cable to The Ws -r Bcnld
Sarajevo, Bosnia, June 28. The Archduke Franz Ferdinand, heir
to the throne of Austro-Hungary, and his morganatic Avife, the Duchess
of Hohenberg, were assassinated while driving through the streets of
this city this morning. They were shot to death after escaping a bomb
that was thrown at their motorcar and warded off by the archduke's
own arm.
They were on their way to a reception at the town hall when
the bomb was thrown. It did not explode until after the archduke's
car Tiad passed and the occupants of the next car, Count Boos Waldeck
and Col. Morizzi, the archduke's aid de camp were injured slightly.
Among the spectators six persons were more or less seriously hurt.
Trie perpetrator was a news
paper compositor named Cabrino-vitch from Trevinje.
Angered by Attack.
The archduke ordered his car halted,
but after he had found out what had
happened he continued on his way to the
town hall, where the councillors with the
mayor at their head awaited them. The
mayor was about to begin bis address of
welcome when the archduke Interrupted
him angrily saying:
"Herr Buergermelster. It Is perfectly
scandalous. We have come to Sarajevo
on a visit and a bomb has been thrown
at us."
The archduke paused for a moment and
then said:
"Now you can go on."
Thereupon the mayor delivered his address to the archduke who made a suit
able reply. The public which by this
time had heard of the bomb attempt,
burst into loud cries of "hurrah."
Miots Rlns list
After going around the town hall for
half an hour the archduke started for the
Garrison Hospital to visit Col. Mori-xl.
who had been taken there after the out
rage. As the archduke reached the corner of Rudolf street two pistol shots were
fired in rapid succession by a young man
named Gavro Prlnxlp. The first shot
struck the Duchess low down on the right
side, while the second hit the archduke
in the neck near the throat and pierced
the Jugular vein.
The duchess became unconscious immidiately and fell across the knee of ner
husband. The archduke also lost consciousness in a few seconds. The motor
car In which they were seated drove
straight to the palace, where army surgeons rendered first aid. but in vain.
Neither the archduke nor the duchess
gave any sign of life, and, the head of
the hospital could only cerUfy that both
were dead.
Frared Second Attack.
The authors of both attacks, who wer arrested promptly, are born Austrian-.
Cabrinovltch worked for a few weeks In
the government printing works at BU
grave. He returned to Sarajevo as a
Servian Chauvinist and made no conceal
ment of his sympathy with the king of
Servla. Both he and the actual murderer
expressed themselves to the police in
most cynical terms about their crimes.
It appears that after the first attempt
on their lives the duchess did not want
the archduke to enter the motercar
again, but the governor of Bosnia. M.
Potlorek. said: "It's all over now. We
haven't got more than one murderer In
Sarajevo."
At this the archduke decided to enter
the car again.
Before their departure from Vienna on
the Journey to Sarajevo the archduke
and duchess went to the chapel In the
palace and spent a long time In prayer.
Recently the archduke has declared
more than once his conviction that he
would not die a natural death.
The mayor of Sarajevo Issued a proclamation to Inhabitants denouncing the
crime and declaring that the confession
of the murderers proves beyond all
doubt that the bomb came from Belgrave f.
Darta from Behind House.
The youth Prlnxlp, who fired the fatal
shots. Is only nineteen. He fired at the
archduke's head and must have been well
Instructed, for he apparenUy was aware
of the well-guarred secret that the archduke always wore a coat of silk woven
obliquely, which no weapon or bullet
could pierce. This fabric Is used for automobile tires and Is puncture proof.
Later, details show that the assassin
darted from his hiding place behind a
house and actually got on the motorcar
In which the archduke and his wife were
sitting and took close aim. first at the
archduke and then at the duchess.
The fact that no one stopped the assassin and that be was allowed to per
petrate the dastardly act Indicate that
that the conspiracy had been carefully
</text>
      </result>      
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045433/1914-06-29/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=archduke+Archduke+Bosnia+EMPEROR+Emperor+Ferdinand+Franz+Josef+Sarajevo</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>
COURTS OF EUROPE SHOCKED.
Aua-slamtlbn of Austrian Heir and
Wife Shock. Ilulrra.
j-ne s. ine terriDie news
from Vienna has thrown all courts of
Europe into mourning. King George.
who only last November entertained the
unfortunate Austrian heir and his wife
at "Windsor, was distressed greatly, and
sent a private message of sympathy to
Emperor Franx Josef. He then Issued
a command that the court shall wear
mourning for one week for his imperial
and royal highness the late Archduke
Franx Ferdinand of Austria.
The lord chamberlain has been com
manded by the King to- announce that
the state ball arranged to take place
Monday evening Is postponed "on ac
count of the lamentable death of Arch
duke Franx Ferdinand of Austria and
the Duchess of Hohenberg."
Berlin, June SI Kaiser Wllhelm re
ceived the news of the tragedy by a
fast destroyer while on board his yacht
racing through the Baltic Sea, In con
nection with the Kiel regretta. His
majesty ordered the race stopped, and
Immediately returned to the steam yacht
Hohenzollern. where he announced:
"The regatta will continue. As for
myself I will return to Berlin."
The Kaiser was deeply affected as he
had been the guest of the murdered
prince early In the present month at
Konopslcht, Bohemia,
Rome, June 28. When the news of the
-Maes! nation of Archduke Francis Fer
dinand and his wife was received here
this afternoon. Pope Plus was In his pri
vate library conversing with his sisters
and niece. Cardinal Merry Del Val gen
tly broke the news. His holiness remain
ed a few minutes spechless and then
went to the chapel where he prayed for
a long time.
Tomorrow's reception Of the Catholic
societies has been cancelled.</text>
      </result>      
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn92053934/1914-06-29/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Archduke+archduke+Austro+Austro-Hungarian+Bosnia+emperor+Ferdinand+Herzegovina+Hungarian+principal+Sarajevo</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>AUSTRIA IS TO
SIFT PLOT IN
DUKPSDEATH
Men Higher Up Believed
to Have Directed Royal
Assassinations.
Punitive Measures Further Embitter Relations Between Two Countries</text>
      </result>      
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn92053934/1914-06-29/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Archduke+archduke+Austro+Austro-Hungarian+Bosnia+emperor+Ferdinand+Herzegovina+Hungarian+principal+Sarajevo</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>
Martial Law Proclaimed.
Sarajevo, Bosnia. June 20. Marital
law has been proclaimed both in the
city and in the district of Sarajevo in
consequence of the assassination yes
terday of Archduke Ferdinand and the
Duchess of Hohenberg.
Death masks of the archduke; and
duchess uere taken today and their
bodies placed in the catafalque of the
chapel of the palace, surrounded by a
terrod the Austrian authorities are
contemplating severe measures
against the Serbs among the inhabi
tants of Austria and Bosnia. These
measures are likely to further embit-
I ter the relations between the two
countries, as well as those between
Austria and Russia, protector of all
the Serbs.
Archduke Francis Ferdinand. It was
asserted today, was well aware of the
danger he was running during his tour
cf Bosnia, which he undertook as in
spector-general of the force's of the
empire. This title was conferred up
on him last year by the emperor. His
chief task was to inspect the Austrian
army wbi-h guarded the Servian fron
tier in the recent Balkan wars and
prevent encroachments by Servian
troops. The Servian minister of Vien
na told Ferdinand of the peril of his
visit to Sarajevo at the present time.
When the archduke and duches3 ar
rived in Sarajevo Saturday some signs
of hostilities were shown by the Serb
portion of the population.
Fly Servian Flags.
Just before the couplo passed
through the city the authorities got
rid of a great display of Servian flags
which people had hoisted Instead of fly.
ing the Austrian colors. Bitterness of
feeling, however, was carried to the
extreme when In the Bosnian diet. I
called to express sorrow over the
death of the archduke, four Servian
deputies appeared in light suits, in
contrast to the sombre black of their
fellow deputies.
Plans of the assassins contemplated,
it Is said. Mowing up of the royal
train when the archduke and his wife
were leaving Sarajevo in case the at
tempt by Gavrico Prlnzip failed. It Is
WATER IN THREE HOLDS
Help Reaches Ship Quickly and
Passengers Transferred
to Another Boat.
floral emblems from all parts of the t learned several bombs were found
country. According to a semi-official
report when Prlnzip f red the fatal
shots Field Marshal Potiorek. gov
ernor of Bosnia, was seated in the
archduke's motor car. Count von
Harrach was standing on th foot
board of the car acting as a shield to
the occupants, of a horn he constituted
Llmself special body guard, after a
bomb hid been thrown a short time
be!ore by Nedeljo Gabrinovich. The
archduke was Joking with the count
about his precautions hen several
shots rang out.
Mortal Wound by Each Bullet. j
The aim of the a-sasin was so true
that each of the bullets inflicted mor
tal wounds. Lieutenant Colonel Mer-
along the Sarajevo railway over which
the arcbdu.and hia wifewpuld have
traveled. Prinzlp's own plans were
carefully laid. He secreted himse'.
behind a building at a spot where It
was necessary for the archduke's car
to slacken speed. Some accounts sar
Prlnzip actually stood on the steps of
the ducal car as he fired the shots.
In Prinzlp's rooms the police today
found a large sum of money which
they say is further proof that he was
the paid assassin of some Servian or
ganization.
Live Only Few Minutes.
Sarajevo, Bosnia. June 29. Arch
duke Francis Ferdinand, heir to the
Austro-Hungarian throne, and the
izzl. wounded by a bomb in the f.rst t Duchess of Hohenberg, his morganatic
attack, was today prrmoiinced out of were shot dead yesterday by a
danger. The LHurv suffered l,v fnum Mudent in the main street of the
Von P-oos Waldeck is insignificant. "osnian capital a short time after they
Croatian students here lodav made i 11 escaped death from a bomb hurled
several attempts to
troops were called
pun:.-h Serbs, but
and maintained
at the royal automobile.
They were slain while
passing
order. Gabricovich was expelled from through the city on their annual visit
to the combined annexed provinces or
Bosnia and Herzegovina.
The archduke was struck full in the
face and the duchess was shot through
the abdomen and throat.
They died a few minutes after reach
ing the palace, to which they were
hurried with all speed.
Bomb and Pistol Used.
Those responsible for the assassina
tion took care that it should prove ef
fective, as there were two assaults, the
Sarajevo two years azo. but recently
was permitted to return throueh the
Intervention of a socialist member of
the Bosnian diet.
Some Servian students here, when
they heard the news of the assassina
tion, shouted: "Thank God, we need
not do it ourselves." They were ar
rested as accomplices of the assassins.
Bomb Thrown.
A bomb thrown by a youth stand
ing on the corner of the main fctreet
f't the Bosnian capital was the signal
th; morning for a serious anti-Servian
cuthreak, wihch troors found consider.!
b!e difficulty in quelling.
The only damage- was slight injury
to a parsing milkman. Th rougher
element siez-d the incident as an ex
cuse for a demonstration. They were
Joined by a n'imbr of Crotiari stud'-nts
cd
ton
clubs, schools and houses and looting
with a
iae head and attacked every thing
Jaa un'il overwhelmed by the police.
London. Eng. June IS. Every dis
patch today from Sarajevo and Vienna
brought add.tlonai evldeice that the
Mass-nation of Archduke Francis
Prd:nejid and the duches of Hohen-</text>
      </result>
        <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88086023/1914-06-29/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=archduke+Archduke+Austria+Austria-Hungary+Bosnia+emperor+Emperor+Ferdinand+Herzegovina+Hungary+SERVIA+Servia+Sophie</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>The official account
was that the archduke's last words
were: "Sophie, you must live for
our children."
Dr. Dynes, commander of the army hospital, embalmed the bodies.
Arrangements are being made to ship
the bodies to Vienna tonight
They will be taken by special train
to Metkovltch, where they will be put
on board an Austrian battleBhlp and
escorted by a squadron of warships to
Trlete. thence by rail to the capital,
where they will arrive Thursday.
It was announced the archduke will
not be burled In the Imperial crypt
at Capuchin church. Vienna, but be
side his wife In a private crypt In the
castle of Amstetten. overlooking the
Danube river.</text>
      </result>
        <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88086023/1914-06-29/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=archduke+Archduke+Austria+Austria-Hungary+Bosnia+emperor+Emperor+Ferdinand+Herzegovina+Hungary+SERVIA+Servia+Sophie</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>NEWS SUMMARY General.
Archduke Ferdinand and His Wife
of Austria are murdered by awasNin.
Riot break out against Servians..</text>
      </result>
       <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88086023/1914-06-29/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=archduke+Archduke+Austria+Austria-Hungary+Bosnia+emperor+Emperor+Ferdinand+Herzegovina+Hungary+SERVIA+Servia+Sophie</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>SERAJEVO. Bosnia. June 29.
Archduke Francis Ferdinand, heir to
the throne of Austria-Hungary, and
the Princess of Hohenberg. his mor
gantic wife, were shot dead yesterday
by a student in the main street of
the Bosnian capital a short time after
thev ha1 SCHwA dpat from hmh
hurled at the rovat auto
They vere knie, whlle passin3
through the city on their annual visit
th anpXfrd nPvInr.p nf Rnsml n.t
Herzegovina.
The archduke was struck full in the
face and the princess was shot through
the abdomen and throat. They died
a few minutes after reaching the pal-
T"" T
VIENNA. June 29. Emperor Fran
cis Joseph's death from the shock f
his heir's assassination Is feared. The
aged ruler seemed dazed Sunday when
told that Archduke Francis Ferdi-
weather is intensely hot. it is fearel
this will add to the collapse of the
emperor.
Serajevo Is under martial la-.
Scores of arrests have been made.
Cabrlnovltch, a newspaper corres
pondent who tried but failed to kill</text>
      </result>
              <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88078751/1914-06-30/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=archduke+Archduke+Bosnia+Emperor+Ferdinand+FERDINAND+Sarajevo+Servia</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>VICTIMS OF ASSASSIN'S BULLETS
Royal Pair Shot
Heir to the Austrian
Throne Shot Dead.
DUCHESS ALSO KILLED
OnlyTwo Shots Fired By Murder
er, Both Taking Effect
TRAGEDY IN BOSNIAN CAPITAL
Archduke Francis Ferdinand and Hi
Morganatic Wife Meet Death at
Sarajevo, Where a Reception Was
Jn Progress, n Their Honor Two
Attempts Made on Ferdinand's-Life
the Duke In the First Instance
Warding Off a Bomb, Which Ex
ploded, Injuring Score of Persons.
Vienna, June 29. Archduke Francis
Ferdinand, nephew of Emperor Fran
cis Joseph and heir to the Austrian
throne, and the Duchess of Hohen
berg, his morganatic wife, were assas
sinated at Sarajevo, the capital of
Bosnia.
Two attempts were made on the
lives of the royal party. A bomb was
thrown aet thir car, which was warded
off by the archduke, and his car pass
ed before It exploded under the next
car, which contained two of his aides
who were slightly Injured.
Later on a man, said to be a young
Servian student, fired two shots from
a revolver at the royal car and the
archduke and tho duchess were killed.
This adds another sad chapter to the
lrfo of tho aged Emperor Francis Jo-
soph during whose reign many grim
tragedies have occurred.
The Archduke Francis Ferdinand
and the Duchess of Hohenberg start
ed out In their auto to attend a recep
tion in their honor at tho town hall.
Suddenly a man named Cabrlnovlcs,
from Trebinje, who was standing
among tho crowd on the sidewalk
throw a bomb at the royal car with
good aim. The archduke saw it com
ing and warded it off with his arm
and tho bomb fell to the street and
did not explode until after the arch
duke's car had passed. When the ex
plosion occurred it resulted in the
wounding of Colonel Morlzzo, aid de
camp to the archduke, and Count Bozz
Waldlok, who occupied tho car Imme
diately behind that of the archduke.
Twenty-six persons among tho specta
tors were more or less seriously In
jured. Archduke Speaks.
The archduke immediately ordered
his chauffeur to stop the car. Ho made
inquiries as to what had happened and
gave orders to have tho Injured at
tended to. After this the procession
to the town hall was continued. Here
tho town councilors with the mayor at
tholr head were awaiting the royal
party to bid them welcome. The
royal party 'entered the hall and the
mayor was about to begin his address
when Archduke Francis Ferdinand In
terrupted him and In an angry man
ner said:
"Horr Burgomaster, it is perfectly
scandalous. Wo have come to Sara
jevo on a visit and a bomb is thrown
nt us." Here ho paused a moment and
then said; "Now you canvgo on." Tho
mayor then delivered his address and
the archduke made a suitable reply.
Couple Killed.
After making the rounds of the
town hall, which occupied half an
hour, the archduke and tho duchess
startod for the garrison to visit Col
onel Morizzi. the archduke's aid, who
was injured by the bomb explosion
and who had been taUon to tho hospital
wm
Down In Street Of
erjevo
In a carrlape after the outrage. As
tif roynl car reached tho corner of
R-,uIolf strpet a man named Gavro
Pr.nzip, who was on the sidewalk,
fired two pistol shots In quick succes
sion at the archduke and the duchess
The man.Avhowas but a short distance
from the car, was a good marksman.
The first shot struck tho Duchess of
Hohenberg low down on the right
side, while the second bullet hit tho
archduke In the neck near the throat
and pierced the jugular vein.
The duchess became immediately
unconscious and fell across the knees
of her husband. The archduke lost
consciousness in a few seconds after
he. was hit. The chauffeur put on full
spce'd and rushed straight to the pal
ace, where an army of surgeons vain
ly tried first aid to the Injured.
Neither the archduke nor the duch
ess gave any sign of life and the only
tblug the head of the hospital could
do was to certify that both were dead.
Assassins In Jail.
Both assassins are In jail. Cabrln
ovlcs is a compositor who worked for
a few weeks at the government print
FRANCIS FERDINAND
Heir to Austrian Throne
the Victim of an Asssassin.
Ing works at Belgrade and returned
to Sarajevo a pronounced Servian
Chauvinist. He made no concealment
of his sympathies with the king of
Seryia. Both Cabrinovlcs and tho
actual assassin. Prlnzlp, expressed
themselves to he police in tho most
cynipal fashion about their crime,
Immediately after the assassination
the mayor of Sarajevo issued a procla
mation denouncing the crime and de
claring that by the confession of the
murderers It was beyond all doubt
that the bomb was brought from Bel
grade, Servia, to Sarajevo. Prinzlp
who fired the fatal shots, Is a student
and Is 19 years of age. He studied
for some time in Belgrado, When in
terrogated by the police he declared
that he had intended for a long time
to kill some eminent person from na
tionalist motives. He denied that he
had any accomplices.
Cabrinovlcs, who Is 21, declared
that he had received the bomb which
lie threw from an anarchist In Bel
grade, whose name he did not know.
He, too, denied that he had any ac
complices. Archduke Francis Ferdinand, who
was heir presumptive to the throne of
Austria, was born Dec. 18, 18G3. His
father, tho Archduke Carl Ludwlg,
was a brother of Emperor Francis Jo
soph, and his mother was Maria An
nunziatu, daughter of Ferdinand II.
of Naples. Francis Ferdinand was
still a hoy when his mothor died.
Francis Ferdinand became the hel:
presumptive When the Crown Prince
Rudolph, the only son of Emueror</text>
      </result>
              <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88078751/1914-06-30/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=archduke+Archduke+Bosnia+Emperor+Ferdinand+FERDINAND+Sarajevo+Servia</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Francis Joseph of Austrla.met a tragic
death in what is known as the Jleyer
ling tragedy, the result of an uncoun
tenanced love for a young baroness.
Aged Emperor Informed.
Vienna, Juno 29. When the news
of the assassination of the Archduke
Francis Ferdinand and the Duchess of
Hohenberg was broken to Emperor
Francis Joseph, who has just recov
ered from a serious illness, ho ex
claimed: "Horrible! Horrible! I am
sorry they spared me,"</text>
      </result>
       <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn99063957/1914-07-24/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Archduke+Austria+Bosnia+demand+Demand+demanded+demanding+demands+DEMANDS+Ferdinand+Hungary+Servia+ultimatum</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Servia Given Until Saturday
Night to Answer and
Answer Right
Berlin, July 24. A "world war"
unless Servia complies with the de
mands Austria has mnde upon it, was.
boing predicted todny by diplomats and
military men here.
The Austrian ultimatum was a sequel
to the recent assassinntion of Archduke
Kraneis Ferdinand, Emperor Francis
Joseph's heir, by a Servian student at
Herajevo, Bosnia province.
It was freely asserted at the time
that the killing was the result of a
fot hntohed at Belgrade by a Pan
Hervian organization with extensive
ramifications in Austria, which has a
largo Servian population in its south
eastern provinces.
It was expected immediately after
the assassination that Austria would
demand an explanation from the Ser
vian government. It delayed so long,
however, that it began to be believed
the emperor was afraid he would preci
pitate a revolt of his own Servian sub
jects if he assumed a belligerent tone.
Late Thursday the Vienna foreign
office suddenly spoke. .Servia was
tilled on, not only to punish those con
concerned in the assassination plot
against Francis Ferdinand, but to sup
press at once the Pan-Servian move
ment. An answer was required by 6 p. m.
Saturday.</text>
      </result>
        <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn99063957/1914-07-24/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Archduke+Austria+Bosnia+demand+Demand+demanded+demanding+demands+DEMANDS+Ferdinand+Hungary+Servia+ultimatum</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Notifies the World.
Paris, July 24. Austria notified all the powers toDay of its demands on
Servia. With the notification it sent
a review of the circumstances attend
ing Archduke Francis Ferdinand's assassination, charging that Servian conspiracies were responsible for his
death.</text>
      </result>
        <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030272/1914-07-26/ed-1/?sp=25&amp;q=Archduke+Austria+Bosnia+demand+Ferdinand+Hungary+principal+Sarajevo+Servia+servia+ultimatum</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
              <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82014682/1914-07-25/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Archduke+Austria+Austria-Hungary+DEMAND+demanding+demands+DEMANDS+Ferdinand+Hungary+servia+Servia+SERVIA+ultimatum</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85058396/1914-07-28/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Archduke+Austria+Austria-Hungary+Austro+Austro-Hungarian+Bosnia+Ferdinand+Hungarian+Hungary+Serbia+Servia+SERVIA</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text></text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-building-titanic</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85042462/1908-04-23/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=White+Star+line</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>WHITE STAR LINE TO BUILD
BIGGEST SHIPS YET PROJECTED
By Associated Press.
LIVERPOOL. April Two new
White Star liners which will be the
largest vessels yet projected will be
laid down at Belfast next June. The
exact measurements of the steamers
have not been given out/but they will
be over 840 feet In length, 78 feet in
breadth and with a gross tonnage of
45,000, or 50,000.
The ships are to be fitted with com
bination turbines and reciprocating
engines guaranteed to maintain a
speed of twenty-one knots. The names
of the vessels are to be Olympic and
Titanic.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1908-10-02/ed-1/?sp=9&amp;q=White+Star+line</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text MAMMOTH LINERS LINERSPUZZLE LINERSPUZZLEOFFICIALS
PUZZLE PUZZLEOFFICIALS PUZZLEOFFICIALSEnglishmen OFFICIALS OFFICIALSEnglishmen
Englishmen Fear 60000Ton 60000TonBoats 60OOOTonBoats 60f000TonBoats
Boats Cant Be BeDocked BeDocked BeDocked
Docked DockedLONDON DockedLONDON DockedLONDON
LONDON Oct 2 2Brltl British h shipbuilding shipbuildingexperts ebipbulkllngexperts shipbuildingexperts
experts are puzzled to know how the theWhite theWhite theWhite
White Star officiate will land passen passengers p paseengem s en engers
gers and cargo fromuthe tront fro tbe a lines two pro prospective protpectie propective
spective 80000 tonn tonnars the Titanic and andOlympic andhmpfc andt
Olympic OlympicThe t ilympicThe hmpfcThe
The Mauretanla and Lusitania of not notmuch notmuch notmuch
much more than half ha1 the proposed proposedcrafts propo proposedcrafts ed edrafts
crafts tonnage have no more room roomthan roomtllan roomthan
than they need to get through the theAmbrose theAmbroee theAmbrose
Ambrose channel and Into the Mersey Merseynt
nt tt t Liverpool LiverpoolThe LiverpoolThe LiverpoolThe
The popular opinion here Is that a avessel afssel avessel
vessel of 0600 tons would have to todo tod tolo
do d Its loading and unloading at sea seaMarine 3eLlarlne seaMarine
Marine statisticians stati tJdans have figured that thatthe thattite
I
the t he tonnage of the e entire Spanish ar arnada armada armada
mada of 129 l ships ships which tried to land landan landn
an n army In England in Queen Eliza Elizabeths EJlzahetbs Elizabeths
beths reign was only 50139 50139Considerable 58139Considerable 13 13Considerable
Considerable progress is being made madewith madewith madewith
with construction work on the Olym Olympic Olympic Olympie
pic In Harland Wolffs yard at atBelfast atBElrut atBelfast
Belfast but the Titanic keel blocks blockswill blockswill l lwill
will not be laid until January January></text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1909-01-03/ed-1/?sp=59&amp;q=White+Star+Titanic</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>ONE MILLION FOR A STARTER
After an expenditure of J1.C00.000 the great stee!
j double gantry which will bo the cradle of th» larg
est two steamship In the world ha« been finished
I at the shipyards of Harland "WoifT. at Belfast.
Ireland. The steamers whose keel blocks haT»
I been laid side by side in this the biggest gantry
j In the world are the Titanic and th« Olympic, of
the White Star Line, and within a year or two
I these leviathans will b« running between New Tori*
and Southampton.
Soon after the two fast Cunarders. too Lusl-
I taria and the Mauretania, had demonstrated that
I one could travel in luxury and at a very high
i speed through tha agency of turbine engines. th«
White Star X-in» announced that it would build
two steamers to beat the Oinarders la length and
breadth, and perhaps In other ways also. It was
reported at the tim» that th« new Whlta Star
liners would be a thousand feet in length, but sub
sequently it was officially announced that they
i would bo 900 feet lons, with a beam of ninety feet.
j When It was decided to build them it was found
that there was no gantry In thm world big enough
to accommodate such monsters, and It was then
that H&amp;rland Wolff began to rip up three of Its
largest gantries and build the hug* steel and con
crete cradle that Is now ready to bold th* Olympic
and the Titanic.
Before th* steel structure which supports th*
i powerful electric travailing cranes was erected a
big concrete base, twenty fret thick, was built upon
sp!le3 driven fifty fe«t into tha ground. The con
crete foundation, in addition to being more firm
than the regular earthen base, has the advantage
of cleanliness, an 1 tools and materials which mar
fall from the cranes la the course of construction
may be found more readily. Parts of deck fittings
end tools have fallen into the ground la gantries
with earth bases and have not been recovered
until the vessel has gilded from Its cradle into the
water.
The construction of the Olympic has been started.
The keel of the Titanic will be laid soon, and
visitors to the shipyards at Belfast will have an
opportunity of seeing the simultaneous csnstrcs
tion. side by side, of the largest two steamers tn
the world. The gantries are so built that any
piece of material, however heavy or awkward, may
be placed and held In whatever position the con
atructora desire. The gantries themselves are more
than a thousand feet in length. 3C3 feet high and
something more than two hundred feet la -Ki&amp;X
T</text>
      </result>
            <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1909-01-03/ed-1/?sp=59&amp;q=White+Star+Titanic</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>A MIGHTY CRADLE FOR GIGANTIC TWINS.
This aantry cost $\COO,COO. It was erected fop the express purooie of corstructinn the two new
White Star steamships, Olympic and Titanic.</text>
      </result>
            <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1909-05-30/ed-1/?sp=59&amp;q=White+Star+Titanic</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>TWO XEW GIAXTS OF SEA.
The Titanic and the Olympic W3l
lie Largest Steamships in World.
Although what will be the largest two steamships
In the world, the Titanic and the Olympic, of the
White Star Line, are mere skeletons just now in
their Lie million-dollar double gantry at Belfast,
Ireland the marine architects know exactly bow
they are going to look when they start on their
maiden passage to this port. From the plans and
specifications the designers have made a wush
drawing showing bow 'he monsters will look when
In the water and ready to sail. Although at nrst
glance the illustration suggests the Isauretania and
Lusitania. with their four gigantic funnels, there
Is something in the appearance of the new levia
thans that Is typical of a White Star steamship.
The great height of the new liners and the broad
sweep of the bridge elves some idea of their 80.J80
tons displacement. The builders have almost elimi
nated the old cusr im of carying masts, «nd In this
respect the targesi ships in the world resemble the
Old Dominion steamers, tha smallest passenger
carrying vessels in the American coastwise service.
All the old Dominior Mners have only one mast.
g the 1
;i' i Titanic.
Thrse tw< vessels are being built simultaneously
sid* by side In a steel gantry that was begun a
year before the keels were laid, and which cost
over a million dollars. The new liners will each
n«» S» feet long, with 92-foot beam. The unusual
beam la equivalent to the length of some of the
fast utenrn yachts of this port. The Olympic and
Titanic will iw» read] for the New York. South
ampton an.i Cherbourg *»*r\ im of the White Star
IJne in 1911. The builders are Harland a Wolff.</text>
      </result>
            <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn93063916/1910-01-08/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=White+Star+Titanic</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>THE
THE WORLDS LARGEST VESSEL VESSELTHE VESSELTHE ESSEIJTHE
THE TITANIC NOW NO BEING BUILT
Here la an architectural picture of the steamship Titanic which Is being beingbuilt beingbunt beingbuilt
built for the White Star line at Belfast also a view of the giant steel cradle cradleiu
iu which the ship Is being constructed The keel of the steamship Is seen in inthe inthe inthe
the lower photograph The White Star company Is to have two of these theselaviathans theselebtthans theseleviathans
leviathans and they will be In commission early in 1911 Their launching launchingwill
will UI signalize a most important era in marine achievement for they will be bobyc beby beby
byc byctil by all odds the largest vessels in the world The Titanic and Olympic will willench wUlh willeach
each h be SCO feet f t in length 92 feet beam 45000 tons register and GOOOO tons tonsdisplacement tonsdl tonsdlstixccnwnt
displacement dl Ilem nt These enormous dimensions are best expressed In comparl comparlS
30115 S The Washington Va hlngton monument is r x55 55 5 feet high and the Metropolitan tower towerlit
lit New Xt York rliy r f ity rises TOO feet Tbe combined tonnage tonnn e of tbe Olympic Olympicand OIrJ11pllukl
and Tlrxink k far fn r exceeds the tonnage ton n e of all It II the vrbs vessels tssl els ls engaged pn n ngld tM1 on both bothskies bothkles bothskies
skies In the hlsi hI Irlt rl conflict of the Spanish armada HfuJ dn Hud nd It Is even more In Interesting Inttresrln inttirestinx
teresting to know ihir t t the Santa Maria was only em I rIt ii 0 feet fi Plat i t Ions IOll a and d 233 tons tonsvet tonhtnhn tonelnirien
htnhn t vet tat nn thl visw yf f 4r1 1 Columbus Journeyed TO th thp new UP world</text>
      </result>
            <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045433/1910-01-23/ed-1/?sp=14/&amp;q=White+Star+Titanic</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
            <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045433/1910-01-23/ed-1/?sp=14/&amp;q=White+Star+Titanic</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
      </result>
            <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1910-07-11/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=White+Star+Titanic</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>By degress v,«, warmed up
7. -_;* cibject o* stear^ship construction, to
•rt^zz. he hsi obßd his life, and declared
£2* Clynplc and Titanic would but*
p^serSsenr ark -"--er- they cams here in
3£-
..-tv, -»--rk or these big Etfiaisshlps is
rilTor. right and day," he "said,
-j "wd have the Olympic ready for
jssciis October Nothing can com
t--c with zs.ezz. in si;* and beauty You
rZI zit z. reflation. In rocm a^d decoratics
xtn. tbese -'cssels cc=s to >*e-v York."</text>
      </result>
                  <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1910-07-11/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=White+Star+Titanic</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>The Olympic and the Titanic will
zzve 2. sp^ed of ti ■cue knots That
is rzzi iced for large ships. Ycu will
rse sc~e rc-sm those vessels The
rt^tfcrsoms -'-'111 be unusually large, ezsd
tier&amp; will te as abundance of room every
■"•isre. Fir example, we win have an ex
c^zzzliy large room off the. dining Bar
tons T-ie-r* people may meet before din-
Sar bold receptlcns. The decoration?
Till be unsurpassed They will be the
fr&amp;sr tliit money can buy They will not
s^rc bs the most magnificent, bui they
Tin i« th&amp; most substantial and solid that
«-ver -J-ere put tote a steamship."</text>
      </result>
            <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1910-07-11/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=White+Star+Titanic</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>time the Titanic will probably
ft ready MSI three or four months after
Olympic sails on her maiden passage</text>
      </result>
      <result>
      <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1910-07-11/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=White+Star+Titanic</id>
      <rel>1</rel>
      <text>The Olympic and Titanic -will be 4S*V
ton vessels. They in called "thcusand
foof ships, but their length win be MO
fee*</text>
      </result>
        <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1911-05-31/ed-1/?sp=5&amp;q=titanic</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>MONSTEB LINER LAUNCHED.
            Steamer Titanic Slides Into Water
            at Belfast.
            BELFAST, May .11.?Enthusiastic
            crowds lined the banks of the River
            lStar line's great steamer Titanic was
            launched with appropriate ceremonies
            this morning.
            The Titanic will enter the White Star's
            New York-Soutl^ampton service late in
            the year, but her sister vessel Olympic
            steams from Southampton two weeks
            hence for New York, and these two sea
            monsters, each 45,000 tons register,
            882Vt feet long and 92 H fo*t broad,
            boast the distinction of being the
            largest and finest, vessels in the world
            These massive ships are also notable
            for the enchanting beauty and the un
            usual spaciousness of their passenger ac
            commodations, and in first, second and
            third class the greatest comfort is prom
            ised. On both steamers swimming pools,
            tennis and hand ball courts, and Turkish
            and electric bath establishments ars
            among the Innovations introduced for the
            pleasure of the passengers.</text>
      </result>
            <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86086633/1912-04-03/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=titanic</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>TITANIC'S MAIDEN TRIP.
Sister Ship to the Olympic of White
Star Line Snls Next Week.
Lorn! on, April The gigantic new
st Mam-ship Titanic of thr White Star
line arrive. todoy at Setithamptt n
from the MinN of her bulkiers at H-l-
fast. She is to be marie re.iriy for herj
maitlen trip across the Atlantl the
atnri al ertotch la scheduled for sVed.
Oaaday af next week. The Titanic is a
sister ship to the Olympic. 8he Is 0
leet hmg and has a d b placement of
r.o 000 tons. The travellmr Ust n the
bb ship will have coo names "Hi its
brt lass roll, in addition to 500 BOO
ot l i lass and third cabin oa
sengt ts. To this will be adder, the
n v oi sua makina a t ui tlo.tiiiK
pojsilatlon of mir1y t.ooe.</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  </topics>